Mr. Men
>> here,
>> Mr. Royo
>> Mr. Glee
>> here,
>> Mr. Craig
>> Miss Diaz
>> here,
>> Mr. Hirs
>> and President B.
>> Council President B is excused this
evening. A few friendly reminders.
Please note this meeting is being live
streamed and recorded. Today's committee
meeting does not have a scheduled public
comment period, but counselors may
invite public comment after each item on
their agenda. If you are making a public
comment, please do so at the microphone.
State your name and address for the
meeting record. Also, please be sure to
silence any cell phones and devices. One
note, item six, resolution 64, will not
be presented during the community
planning committee uh this evening and
has been stricken from the agenda. I'll
hear a motion for the approval of the
August 11th, 2025 committee meeting
minutes.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Motion. Do I hear a second?
>> Second.
>> Motion in a second. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. Matt.
>> I.
>> Mr. Roya.
>> Mr. Glee.
>> I.
>> Miss. Craig.
>> Miss Diaz.
>> I.
>> Mr. Harsh.
>> We'll kick it over to the personnel
committee. Councelor Clees.
>> Thank you, Vice President. The personal
committee has two item on the agenda for
tonight. The first item is the
nomination of Kisha Finny for
reappointment to the public art advisory
board. So, Miss Finny has been working
has been serving on the board for some
time and her term has expired and she's
willing to be reappointed as an
alternate alternate uh member of the
board.
And uh I'll open up for any comments,
questions from
for more than members of the committee.
>> Council colleagues,
>> thank you. I would just like to say that
uh Miss Finny has been a great public
advocate for art here in the city and I
look forward to seeing her reappoint.
>> Thank you for your comment. Councelor
>> Council Cle, uh just also want to add um
many of you know uh Kesha through her
work uh as an artist here in Lancaster
City and as someone that serves on that
board. Um, I think it's really important
that we have local artists on that
board. Um, so I'm really glad that we're
reappointing Kesha.
>> Thank you, councelor, for your comments.
Any other comments or questions from
console as a whole,
>> from the public?
Hearing none, I'll make a motion to move
this nomination to our next console
meeting.
>> Second.
>> All in favors?
>> I.
>> Thank you. And the next item is the
nomination of uh Stephen Campbell for
reappointment to the sewer appeals
board. So Mr. So there isn't much to say
about this reappointment. Um
so I just want to thank Mr. Campbell for
willing to continue to serve on the
board. I'll open up for questions and
comments from other members of the
committee and council
from the public.
I'll make a motion to move this
nomination to our next council meeting.
>> Second.
>> All in favors?
>> I.
>> Thank you. That concludes the personal
committee. Vice President.
>> Thank you, councelor colleagues. We'll
move to the finance committee. Uh this
evening we have one item on our agenda,
administration bill number 6, 2025,
which is authorizing the issuance of a
general obligation note. With that, I'll
invite Director Campbell uh to introduce
the bill.
>> Good evening.
If you can just leave yours off.
Sometimes I get feedback until till
you're ready to talk. Sorry, we have
some issues with the mics. Um so tonight
we're introducing an ordinance for the
general obligation uh an ordinance of a
general obligation note. Um, this note
is for interim bank financing for the 42
inch water transmission mainline that
we've discussed on several other
occasions over the last year or so. Um,
the project has also been included in
our capital plan for a few years and is
included in the capital budget that
we've been presenting since June. And
uh, you will see the first reading of
that ordinance for the capital budget on
September 9th. Uh because this project
is for the water main um this debt will
be financed through the water enterprise
fund and will not affect the general
fund.
In March um you may remember we reviewed
uh as we reviewed the 2025 bond
financing. We discussed that we would be
returning to you later this year for
financing for this project. Um so this
is us returning to you for this project.
Um, and as you may recall, we included
this debt in our projections when we
showed the principal and interest costs
uh for the bond um on the graphs that
you received for that bond uh because we
knew that this project was coming. So,
as a reminder, this project will
ultimately long-term be financed through
Penvest. Um, Penvest requires that the
project be shovel ready before they will
loan funds. So all of the design,
engineering, permitting must be
completed and the work needs to be ready
to start uh before Penvest will award
the loan. Because of the timing of some
of the grant funds that we were awarded
for this project and because of some of
the current uncertainties for timing of
procurement of equipment and materials,
we would like to get orders out for the
materials for this project before
Penvest will award the funds for the
long-term funds. Um, so that the grant
funds are assured of being used and so
the project can start as soon as
possible when we get the loan funds from
Penvest.
If you recall, we initially thought that
we would include some of this funding
for the materials in the bond financing.
Um, however, Penvest will not refinance
permanent um or bond financing. Um, so
this is an interim bank note financing
and this will allow us to move all of
the costs eventually into the Penvest
loan as they do allow interim financing
to be included in long-term debt. This
will keep interest costs down very
significantly for us um as Penvest
interest is lower than bond financing
and it will make um the in the interim
financing well worth um the savings and
interest expense and Darl will talk a
little bit more about that as well. Um
the interim financing is also structured
as uh like a line of credit. Um so we
will only draw down and therefore only
pay interest on what we actually need to
use. So, I'll now turn it over to Darl
to provide more context.
>> Uh, good. Uh, uh, uh, thank you, Tina,
um, for that introduction and great to
be before you again. As indicated, uh,
we talked about this earlier this year.
I know time flies. Here we are in
September already. Um,
I put before you uh a narrative and uh
some
one financing schedule and one graph. So
hopefully we can walk walk right through
that and uh make sure you have an
understanding of what we're doing and
why we're doing it. Uh and and Tina
touched on a lot of this, but uh clearly
you're moving forward with the water
transmission line project. Um
I'm not the engineer in the public works
but as I understand it that's going to
uh you know provide resiliency and and
redundancy to the soil water main that
was put in put in place and put in the
ground in uh 1955 uh 1955 and uh you
know with that it's certainly reaching
to towards the end of its useful life.
Um so the total cost of the project is
estimated at $41 million. Um, as Tina
indicated, permanent financing for the
project is expected to be secured by
Pennsylvania Infrastructure Investment
Authority. Most of you know it as
Penvest. Um, and the city and its
project engineer in the process of bring
moving that application forward. Um, and
uh, again, as Tina indicated, uh, you
know, due to the expected time required
until the city is prepared to make that
application and more importantly
actually receive the funding, um, you
know, it behooves you to secure this
interim financing in the amount of about
$32 million.
Uh so that you'll can pre-order uh and
purchase the primary materials being the
pipe hydrants uh and fittings etc. By
having those uh available when you
actually go forward and bid the
construction phase of the project, you
should absolutely expected that you will
you know one uh be able to proceed in a
more timely manner to move the project
forward and maybe importantly from a
cost savings standpoint
is you should get uh better bids for the
construction phase because the
contractor will know when they get when
they put the bid in and get awarded
they're going to get to work right away
as opposed to you know starting to work
six months later with you know some
unknowns. So I I really think and that's
this is clear this whole plan was really
obviously put together by uh Department
of Public Works and your engineers etc.
So, we're just helping move that forward
and facilitate it with this interim
financing. Um, right now we're the the
city's at its uh sort of immediate or
crucial requirement. I don't want to get
too technical, but you may have heard
this before. Uh, in order to move
forward with with securing the interim
financing that we're going to do, you
get what's called a letter of no
prejudice uh from Penvest. What that
means uh in in plain vanilla talk is
that by having that letter of no
prejudice, you can now incur the costs
and potentially even pay the costs um
before you actually get the penvest
financing. So it's kind of no prejudice
that you can include those costs and
roll it into the financing. Um so at the
end of the day, the interim financing
will be paid off and rolled into uh the
lower interest rate penvest financing
again as Tina said instead of including
them in the 2025 bonds. So a lot of
interest cost savings by rolling the
primary cost being the materials into
the pen loan and not doing it under what
would be more conventional financing. So
uh with that um page two
uh is really putting together the the
schedule not the project schedule
intertwined with the financing schedule.
Uh I want to stress this is tentative. I
think you all understand we try to
remain fluid and nimble. Uh and I'll
also stress that this is a sequencing
schedule. You know, I'm going to put
dates here, but uh understand that if
you know, kind of an early event slips,
that means the whole schedule's going to
slip. So, I think it also just gives you
a framework how these all intertwine and
move together. So, of course, we're
giving you the presentation this
evening. Um in midepptember we expect to
get the letter of no prejudice again
that critical document from Penvest. Um
and with that letter of no prejudice in
hand we would actually we Concord would
actually move forward with the interim
financing request proposals uh to be
sent to the banks and then we'd hold the
city council at at the city council
meeting we would hold the first reading.
That may or may not be on September 9th.
It may be on September 23rd. Again, I
think we're going to stay need to stay a
little bit nimble there. Um, and then
moving forward on this timeline, then in
mid-occtober, we would get the bank
proposals. Um, obviously we review them
and make a recommendation as to the best
proposal. And at the city council
meeting in October, whether it be
October 14th or October 28th, have the
second reading actually accepting a
proposal. and critical critical we must
have the letter of no prejudice in hand
before you award financing if not we
risk having this project not being
eligible for pendas so obviously we're
very cautious of that uh and wouldn't
bring it to you beforehand
um then as a current schedule uh on
October 29th uh the city plans do
actually submit the uh permanent
financing application to Penvest
um then we
close on the inter financing in mid o
mid November. Having that inter
financing in place that assures you you
have funds in the amount of the $32
million to actually place that order.
Again, you wouldn't want to place order
for $30 million of of uh equipment or
materials that you don't have financing
in place for. Um
and then so you can and that project
lead time for those project materials is
four to six months. So that's really the
the lead time that you're gaining uh in
your schedule by doing the interim
financing. Uh then with the uh Penvest
application towards the end of October
uh the next PENve best meeting for the
award of financing uh is in January of
2026.
Uh again moving forward in the timeline
in February February
the project materials would be received
and you would be moving forward with the
construction bid phase. uh for for bid
an award. So again, then you'd be ready
to move forward with the actual um
actual project commencement. Then in uh
April and May of 2026, you'd have your
legislative process or ordinance process
for the permanent Penvest financing. Uh
project construction would begin. We
would expect to close on the Penvest
permanent financing. And when you get
the Penvest permanent financing in hand
and in place, you would actually pay off
the interim financing for the for the uh
materials portion. Um the project is
expected to be completed in April of
2027.
We are going to let the interim
financing uh have an extra year uh of
its maturity. Again, trying to be
cautious. Um we all know projects can
can get delayed. And also the there's a
secondary purpose of the interim
financing not only to bridge the
materials acquisition but you can also
use that interim financing for like cash
flow for the project because if ever the
reimbursements that come from Penvest
would not be quite timely. You want to
have the interim line of credit is
serving a dual purpose. It's the
materials phase and it's also the
potential delay that you might have from
Penvest because they work on a
reimbursement basis.
Um uh the most we can have is a year. Uh
we're allowed to have the interim
financing be uh one year after the
estimated completion date. So that
should should be sufficient for you.
Um
Tina touched it on the top of page
three. The interim financing is on a
draw down basis or a line of credit.
again minimize on the interest expense.
Uh the interim financing will also
provide an amount to pay the interest on
the interim financing during the project
phase and that's to avoid the budgetary
impact. Um you know you're going to have
to go through the the PUC process etc to
be able to to raise water rates outside
the city. So um the plan would be to
have the the interim financing also be
available to pay the interest to the
extent you want to do so. not a
requirement to do so but it's available
to do so uh should that uh be necessary
within the budget. Uh the next bullet I
I uh mentioned that the inter financing
will mature in June of 28 to be that
additional one year provide the project
cash flow. Um, moving forward on page
four,
um, kind of like a sources and uses here
of the of the interim financing. Again,
two critical points. Provide the funds
to order and purchase the materials and
to provide the bridge loan or cash flow
loan during the project phase. So, the
total cost of the financing will be $32
million.
Um, that's providing really four
components. uh the $30 million for the
project materials to be purchased. Uh
estimated capitalized interest or
interest on the interim financing of
about $900,000.
The financing cost and about a million
dollar reserve again for that project
cash flow need. Remember, you won't draw
on that. You won't use that unless you
absolutely need it, but it's there in
case you need it. So, that's how we
arrived at uh inter financing note of
$32 million.
The next schedule is really presented as
a not to exceed amount. It's kind of
like I have to show you that, but no way
do we expect the interest expense to be
that great because again of the draw
down and the prepayment feature.
Um and lastly on page five again a graph
similar that you have seen before and we
actually showed you as a looking forward
uh back in back in March when we were
doing 2025 bonds. So the red bars here
are the existing uh water fund debt
service and the blue lines are the uh
expected uh water fund debt service
after what would be the $41 million
pendest financing and how you and how
you step into it. So overall water fund
debt service will go from about 15.1
million uh next year uh up to about 18.5
million uh beginning 2020
um questions or um so entertain those.
>> Can I just add quickly to I don't
don't think anybody from DPW is here u
from public works but I did just want to
say the timeline might seem a bit
aggressive. Um and we did talk to them
about that uh quite a bit. Um, so it
sounds like uh we will have three
different contractors doing the work
because we are able to get all of the
materials together where it's easier to
to be able to do that. Um, so it'll kind
of be work going on simultaneously.
Um, which will increase the speed of it.
Um, but one of the main reasons for that
is um, and I won't get into all of the
details, but to um, try to ensure that
we can get this in our PUC rate case as
quickly as possible. um just because we
know it's such a big project and a large
portion of it is um for out for outside
of the city um as well as as some
inside. So um just wanted to comment on
that schedule. And if there's questions
about specific questions about the um
the schedule or the project itself, we
can uh have public works comment on
those at a later date.
>> Thank you for the presentation. Um a
couple questions. Uh, with this being
short-term financing, is the rate
variable or is this a fixed rate? I see
here there's a 5%.
>> Yeah, interest rate.
>> That's an estimate. Um, actually, when
we do our request proposals, we will ask
for both variable rates uh and fixed
rates. Probably your preference would be
to have a fixed rate. Um, but with the
short-term nature, we're going to see
what we get. You know, kind of like bid
it out or or ask for both and do an
analysis and figure out what's more
beneficial. If we get kind of a very
aggressive or favorable variable rate.
Um, and we'll certainly get a cap rate.
You know, just look at what the variable
is in the cap versus what the fixed rate
is is that we get. So,
>> thank you. And my second question is,
uh, with the short-term financing being
32 million, is the remaining 9 million
estimated the estimated construction
costs? Great.
Great. Any uh further questions from the
committee? Mayor Sorzi,
>> not not the committee, but I just want
to thank um Tina and the Department of
Public Works. Um and with the assist
from Conquered, I think one of the
things that's very momentous about this
and I just don't want it to get lost in
in the mix is the point that Tina was
making about the aggressive schedule. Um
in the past we have not been um we have
been borrowing money to do the design
and then um and then do the construction
and we have uh had large sums of money
that have been sitting not being
utilized in um in an aggressive time
fashion. And that is a habit that we
have been trying to work ourselves out
of I think for the last eight years. Um
because when you borrow money, you
should be spending it very quickly.
Within three to four years, you that
money should be in the ground and then
that should be coming back. Um this is
going to be really aggressive. Um with
uh a borrowing here we are at the end of
almost you know the end of 2025 2028
this project is complete. So two years
in the these are the kinds of benchmarks
that council should be asking for in the
future to really understand if the
capital projects are indeed ready and
that we're going to spend the money in
the time frame that we need to. And so I
really applaud um Tina, Director
Campbell, the directors Campbell, Steve
and Tina, uh for really leading off on
this work and the kind of planning that
went into the capital planning effort
overall is allowing us to do this. And
council should also be really um
monitoring the frequency in which we are
going to Penvest for rate um case
increases because as Tina mentioned this
is a very this is a once in a generation
um uh improvement that is being made and
while it's $40 million for this phase
it's a lot more than that when you add
all three phases together.
>> Thank you for that context Mayor Sarra.
Any questions or comments from the
finance committee? Any
questions or comments from council as a
whole?
Council
>> Hirsh. Thank you. Um and this might not
be the question for you. This might
actually be more of a question for
public works. Um but I just see that
there's an estimated four to six month
delivery um for the materials. How solid
do we feel about that given um I mean I
don't know what if anything is being
sourced from overseas but with the trade
situation um kind of being volatile I'm
just curious if the city has any
thoughts on that.
>> I think that is probably more of a
question for public works. I will say I
I asked a few different ways um if they
feel confident with that four to six
months and they were they were feeling
pretty confident about it. So I think
they can probably give more details but
Thank you, councelor Hirs. Any
additional questions or comments from
full counsel?
>> Thank you, Mr. Vice President. Um, and
thank you for the presentation. This was
very helpful. Um, my only question is,
and you may have answered this, when we
do have the RFPs from the banks, is that
going to be something that council will
approve or is that something that the
administration will unilaterally take
care?
Um so typically we receive those RFPs
back and then bring the proposed RFP
from the administration to council. Um
you would see that with the second
reading of the ordinance. So you would
see the full the full amount then. Am I
saying that? Am I stating that
correctly?
>> Yeah. The ordinance itself will will
accept uh the proposal that is being
recommended.
>> Thank you. And that concludes my
questions. Mr. Vice President, thank you
councelor Med. Any additional questions
or comments from council?
Any from the public?
Great.
Thank you both for the presentation this
evening. Um I will move to or I have a
motion to move bill number six to the
September 23rd meeting for first
reading.
>> Second.
>> Motion in a second. All those in favor?
I
>> I that concludes the finance committee.
Uh we'll move on to community planning.
Councelor Craig.
>> Thank you, Council Vice. Um the we have
five items on the agenda this evening.
First being the review of the historical
commission. Review of the historical
commission recommendation for demolition
of a garage at 53 North Water Street.
Thank you.
>> Great.
>> Good evening, mayor. Good evening,
council.
This um res resolution is a
recommendation from the historical
commission to approve a demolition of a
two bay, one-story freestanding cement
block garage behind where the bread
peddler is at 53 on 53 North Water
Street. Uh it is
uh it was built in the 1940s and uh they
did receive zoning approval on July 23rd
and the historical commission is
recommended recommended approval at
their meeting on August the 7th for
demolition of this and it will remain as
a surface parking lot.
>> Thank you. That's pretty cut and dry.
Are there any questions from the
committee?
>> Council Greg.
just um is the parking lot short-term or
have they mentioned any long-term use
potentially for that space there?
>> It's a pretty small space. In fact, the
reason why they want to demolish it is
because they feel like it's not safe to
try and pull two cars in there. So, I
believe it's going to remain as a
surface parking lot as far as I
understand.
>> Thank you.
>> Great.
>> Are there any questions from council as
a whole?
>> Just a comment. I did look at it on
Google Maps and yeah, it's it's going to
be like a space or two at most. So,
>> that's what
um well then that will do that. Um I'll
make a motion to move this forward to
September
9th.
>> Second.
>> All those in favor?
Thank you. Um the next item we have on
the agenda is administration resolution
authorizing an application for local
shares
and we have several applications for
local shares. So I think what we're
going to do
>> I'm sorry council I think we have
resolution number 60 on the agenda next.
>> 60 oh thank you very much.
Okay. Administration resolution number
60. I skipped right over top of it. My
apologies.
Amending a projection easement granted
to Hacker Arcade Condominium
Association.
And I'm glad you're here. So, take it
away.
>> Thank you. The original resolution was
passed by city council on May 14th,
2024. Um, and if you recall, it granted
an easement so that balconies uh for the
condominium condominiums can hang over
Northwater Street and West Grant Street.
Uh the original uh easement agreement
incorrectly listed the required height
of the balconies as 15 feet above the
street, but the amended easement
agreement is intended to correct the
minimum height to 13 feet and 6 in which
is in compliance with the city
ordinances current in currently in place
and that is the only change to the
easement agreement this evening.
>> Thank you. I have no questions about
that. Um are there any questions from
the committee?
questions from council as a whole or
comments.
>> Uh just a quick question. Um
if it were up to me, I would probably,
you know, if I could wave a magic wand,
me personally, I would take uh traffic
off of the West Grant Street portion by
market. Um but I do know that some box
trucks do go through there every now and
then. Are we okay with the height in
light of that? don't know if it would be
an issue or not, but it's just a
question I I had.
>> That is a very good question. Um, this
came through the Department of Public
Works and the right ofway engineers. So,
I will have to get back ask them and get
back with you on that.
>> They probably Yeah, they probably only
overhang like the sidewalk. So, I I'm
sure it's fine. But
>> how far is the bump out? I guess that's
the question.
Thank you, Council H. That was a great
question.
Um,
I'll make a motion to move um
administration resolution 60 to full
counsel on the 9th.
>> Second.
>> All those in favor?
>> I.
>> Thank you. Now, we will move on to
administration resolution 61
authorizing
to local shares account program by the
Lancaster city Lancaster Public Library
and then there are several local shares
accounts that we will review.
>> Thank you, Director Campbell.
>> Thank you. Um, so before we get into the
resolutions, I wanted to just give a
brief overview of the ler of the local
shares account or LSA grant program.
I'll refer to it as LSA this evening.
Um, this is a p this is a Pennsylvania
statewide program that's funded through
the Commonwealth Financing Authority and
it distributes state gaming revenue. Um,
so it's now the fourth year of this
statewide program. There was there were
some individual counties that did it
previously. Um, but this is the fourth
year for the statewide program. So
grants can be awarded from $25,000 up to
a million dollars through this program
and there's no match requirement. Um,
makes it very popular for um community
benefit organizations in the community.
Um the grantee must be a governmental
agency of some sort. Um so we do get
many requests from community benefit
organizations to apply for this program.
Um and then we serve as the grantee um
and they serve as the subgrantee.
More than one grant can be awarded to
the governmental agency or the
municipality. Um and previous years we
have received multiple grants for the
community through this program. So just
uh to give you a a summary, in the first
three years, we have made 35
applications for LSA grants on behalf of
uh community benefit organizations and
and a couple of city projects as well.
12 of those applications were awarded at
least partially um and it totaled uh
$6,923,000
in funds um to the to the community,
which is great. Um and then the
remaining 23 grants, 12 were denied um
but 11 are still pending um from last
year. The awards have not been made yet
for those um applications.
So the YSA funds can be used for
acquisitions of property, purchase of
equipment, or construction projects,
either new or remodeling. And you'll see
a range of all of those projects in
these requests.
Um because this is a state grant and we
are the grantee, we must have a
resolution from council allowing us to
apply for each individual grant. Um
these resolutions commit the city to
applying for the grant, but it does not
guarantee funding, nor does it risk
anything for the city. The applications
are due November 30, November 30th, and
we anticipate uh probably 10
applications this year. Um and we'd like
to have each of the organizations attend
one of the council meetings or committee
meetings um between now and November
30th to talk about their projects um so
that you can as you review the
resolutions you can see the projects. Um
so you'll see several projects on
various agendas in the next couple of
months.
So tonight we have three of them on the
agenda since um since we struck the last
one. Um, each of these, well, one of
these is present tonight. Um, and the
other two will be present at one of the
council meetings in September. Um, so
I'm not going to talk long about the the
two that aren't here since you will hear
from them later. Um, but I can I can
talk about them now or wait and do each
resolution separately.
>> Um, I think we can do them now.
>> Okay.
>> Um, so the first resolution is for the
Langster Public Library. It's a It's a
million dollar uh grant request and it
is for uh it's to purchase actually um a
parking lot close to their um book
resort um project on North Marshall
Street. Um it will provide some income
for them as well as a place to continue
to have people um park. So I will let
them talk about that. They are attending
the council meeting um next week on
September 9th.
>> Excellent.
>> Um and then I'm gonna here. I don't
believe anybody from HDC is here. Don't
see anybody.
>> I don't see anyone.
>> So, theirs is also a request for a
million dollars. Um they are um uh
working on phase three of the College
Avenue redevelopment. Um and the phase
three is a broader um phase that really
has some mixed use mixed income space in
it. So, again, I will let them talk
about that in more detail.
>> Excellent.
>> And then um the last one is Anchor
Langster and they actually here this
evening. So, I'm gonna ask
>> Wonderful
>> Patty to come forward
>> while she's coming. There's is also a
request for a million dollars. Um, and
it is for renovations to the day shelter
at Tenfold, but I'll let her do the
explanation.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Thank you for taking the
opportunity to hear what I have to say
tonight. Um, so Ankor Lancaster is a
nonprofit that works with the homeless
and lowincome here in Lancaster City.
Right now we are our program is housed
inside of First United Methodist Church.
We've been renting space there for the
last nine years. We started as just a
breakfast program and um last year I
think we served 42,000 meals to our
hungry neighbors. Um, we like to listen
to what our neighbors have to say. And
we found out that many of them were
taking baths in sinks at uh market, at
CVS, and we had showers. So, we started
a shower program. The goal was to do 12
showers a week. Last year, we did 6,000
showers. So, yeah.
Um and then during COVID we realized
that all the public buildings were
closed and so we started a day center.
It just seemed to make sense to us. Um
and then we started a laundry program
and started a case management program.
Our case management program help people
with um
building resumeumés, applying for jobs,
uh finding housing,
uh helping connect them to medical
services, drug rehabs, and just really
meeting them wherever wherever they are.
Uh we partner with a many different
agencies here in the city. We work with
um Lancaster General. We work with Penn
State Health. We work with UPMC. We work
with the social workers at the um police
station. We work with the social workers
at Tenfold and from the food hub and uh
the outreach worker who works with the
um merchants here in the city. And so
our space at the day center, it started
as just a temporary winter shelter and
then we did a temporary summer shelter
and we quickly outgrew our space. Our
space was only able to hold less than 20
people and literally it was wallto-wall.
And so we've been searching for another
place for our day center and we are just
so grateful for Tenfold and when they
did the temporary shelter last year that
one of my case workers and I went down
and volunteered for the overnight
shelter and as I'm standing in that
shelter I was just like h wonder if we
could be here too. So we started a
conversation with Tenfold and they just
have welcomed us with open arms. Uh we
went for one week. Uh we've been there
for eight months and we're looking to
make more of a permanent partnership
with Tenfold to so we can heat that
area, cool that area much more
efficiently than what it is being done
now.
With that, we will need to do some
construction of a temporary um space,
but something that we'd put up a wall.
Um and I feel bad saying that we want to
put up a wall because we're trying to
tear walls down with our neighbors, but
we can put in heating and we can put in
cooling. And that is our phase one um
plan. But we're also exploring whether
we will move the entire program down to
the tenfold space where we would put in
a commercial kitchen. And if you've been
in the garage, it's very large and it
would be the kitchen, the dining room,
and the day center. And then we would
there's an annex that is next to it,
which would be offices. It would be our
laundry. It would be place for case
management to work. Also would be for
bathrooms and showers. And that is the
request for the funding uh for that
program.
>> Thank you so much for that description.
>> That's good. Are there any questions
from the committee?
>> I just want to thank you for your
services for our community.
>> I know it's hard. I've worked with
Border Rescue Mission. I volunteer
>> to feed them. That's about as far as I
go. But it's nice to talk to them and
where they're at in life and how they
want to improve their life and these
services are really important for them
to find work and also shelter. So, thank
you so much.
>> You're welcome.
>> Any further questions from the committee
>> council as a whole.
>> Thank you, council. just also echoing um
so much gratitude for the work that Anko
does and in particular the willingness
to collaborate with other organizations
um in the city I think is really
commendable and it shows you know that
we can do a lot to meet a lot of need um
and I think what I hear you saying when
you're talking about all these things
meals showers place to be place to be
out of the the heat or the cold like
you're meeting immediate needs and when
we collaborate
as as you know all every one of us
that's a part of this community if we
work together we can do a lot more and
so that's one thing that I've admired as
I've watched the work that you guys have
done and the way that your programming
has grown over the years so I just want
to really commend you guys best of luck
with the application
>> thank you
>> any further questions from council as a
whole for comments
councelor
>> corre first thank you for sharing the
outline of the vision. It seems very
exciting. Um, just because we have the
mics in front of us, if there's an
opportunity for folks to invest their
time or treasure into the organization,
how can they find out more information?
>> So, they can visit our website at
anklancaster.org.
Uh, there is um information there about
volunteering and about giving.
>> I know it's a passionate subject in our
community today. the more that we can
help invest our resources into
organizations like yours, I think it's
worth mentioning. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Can I just add to I believe the total
project is about 1.6 million. Is that is
that correct? At least that's what my
notes are saying. So
>> So we need a little bit more.
>> We need a little bit more is what I'm
saying.
>> Uh no, it is um it's actually two and a
half to three million.
>> So it's gone up.
>> Yes. um for the day center alone to to
to put the wall up and lower the ceiling
a little bit and put in the unit for
heating and cooling is about 140,000.
>> Thank you.
>> Are there any questions or comments from
the public?
>> Want to step to the mic over here?
Hold on. Somebody's coming to help you.
>> Robert Mlan, 123 South Christian. Why?
This is a small item on your calendar
here, but you keep talking about, well,
you don't, but I mean, it always comes
up, parking throughout Lancaster City,
and I'm always wondering about all the
massive parking lots that we have. Why
can't a lot of them be permeable
so we don't have all this water running
into the source?
>> Okay, thank you.
I think we'll address that in a little
bit.
Okay. Um, can we do these can we do the
local shares together or should we do
them individually?
>> Okay. Thank you so much. I'll make a
motion to move um the local shares
applications
administration resolution 61
and 63 to full counsel on the 9th.
>> Second.
>> All those in favor?
>> I
thank you. Um council vice that
concludes community planning.
>> Thank you councelor Craig. I forgot I
was running the meeting today.
We'll move on to the public safety
committee. Councelor Diaz.
>> Yes. The public safety committee has
administration resolution 592025
adopting the Lancaster County hazard
migration plan. And we do have a
presentation that will be done by Deputy
Fire Chief Christopher Dong, city
emergency management coordinator.
There you go.
>> Good evening, council. Good evening,
mayor. Um, this is a culmination of a
two-year project um that I've been
working on with the Langster County uh
emergency management agency and fellow
uh municipal leaders um in emergency
management to update the county hazard
mitigation plan. Um the original plan
was written in 2019 and this is the
first revision of this plan. Um
the importance of the plan writing and
revising is to make sure that um we have
a current
idea of what our hazards are in each
municipality in the county. Um so it's
it's a it's a very thorough project. Um
usually takes a year, took an extra year
this time. Um, but it goes through and
they solicit information from all the
municipalities, all the public
utilities, all the school districts,
pretty much everybody that comes in
contact with Langster County um, in the
municipalities, and they uh, try to get
a good idea of what the hazards are,
both natural, man-made, um, criminal in
certain circumstances. Um, and then this
massive plan that's 674 pages. um gets
written and gets presented to each
municipality for adoption. And what this
does for us, it's a written record of
our known um hazards in our
municipalities and then it allows us to
submit and apply for grant funding to
mitigate those known hazards ahead of
time so we can reduce their impacts if
they were to occur in our communities.
Um, so the team that brought Lanster
City into this this project is um
there's probably at least a dozen of us
that have added to uh the writing of
this plan. U so me being here is trying
to get it adopted. Um I can give you
kind of an idea of what how thorough the
plan is, but like I said, it's 674
pages. It's quite massive. Um but it is
very thorough. Most of the hazards in on
our side of the plan are public works
driven. Um they are water and wastewater
utility projects um that we're
projecting to address in the next five
years. Um so it there's no guarantee
that we're going to get them
accomplished in the next five years, but
it is a guess. Um that way we can apply
for the funding to supplement those
projects.
Thank you so much. Um, I do have a
question for you. Would this be with the
grants? Would that be in addition to the
FEMA grants as well or is is that all
combined?
>> So, there used to be two FEMA grants
that um we were eligible for. One of the
gr one of the grants is no longer
active. Um, the grant that is still
active is the hazard mitigation uh grant
program. It's centered around natural
hazard resistance which is like
earthquakes, floods,
um
winter storms, summer storms, that kind
of stuff. So, uh not exactly what we
were hoping for for available grants,
but we will we will still take advantage
of the grants that we are eligible for.
>> Thank you for that. Do um does the
committee have any questions?
Councelor Diaz, if I may.
>> Go ahead.
>> Thank you for the presentation. Um, one
question I had is with the county
recently ending its uh partnership with
the hazmat um environmental fire rescue
company. Does that have any to do with
this uh proposal or is that going to
affect the plan at all?
>> It's a good question. Um, so the plan
addresses hazardous materials hazards in
the county. Um so this is a little bit
more big picture um to that whereas
that's more um response.
I think this plan drives the response
delivery that any hazardous materials
response team would um provide coverage
to. So I don't know if it's completely
related. um certain they're symbiotic in
that um any response team will take the
information identified in this plan and
use it to their advantage.
>> Yes, because I did see that they were
planning to work with a neighboring
county. I just wanted to make sure that
the work that we're doing would cover
any outside third party that is coming
in and
>> Absolutely. U so they're currently
contracting with Lebanon County. Um, and
we actually had an incident since they
took over um that we've that we worked
together on. It went very seamless. Um,
we don't see a difference
so far. Um, but we're looking forward to
the future.
>> Thank you. And that concludes my
questions.
>> Was that the rotten eggs?
>> That was the rotten eggs. Yes.
>> Just just so everybody knows, there was
an incident with the spill of rotten
eggs. So, uh, but that was our hazard
incident. It was nothing more than very
smelly rotten egg.
>> It was enough.
>> Were they rotten before the accident?
>> Yes.
>> Uh, any other questions for full
counsel?
>> Then I will go ahead then to move this
to full counsel on September 9th.
>> Second.
>> All in favor? I
>> and the next thing in the agenda is a
bill
number five, 2025 to create a community
police review board.
One second.
I believe that you were going to reach
out to Chief Mendes and I uh to have a
discussion um per your comments at the
last meeting. I haven't received any
response from you or or the uh chief,
but um you're welcome to um bring that
forward.
>> Uh please feel free to forward me the
email request that you sent to chief and
I because I didn't receive it. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> And I will go ahead and hold this until
we receive response from the mayor and
chief Mendes.
>> And and I would just qualify that if I
may until there's a meeting, right? You
had requested a meeting with chief and
I.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thank you. That would be all for public
works. I mean for public safety,
>> I believe. And Mr. Harris, please
correct me. I believe we need an action
to table this.
>> Yes, that'd be the best.
>> Councelor Diaz, if you would like to
make a motion to table this.
>> I'll go ahead and make a motion to table
this till the second, I guess, meeting
of city council.
And so hopefully between now and the
next meeting, the second meeting, we'll
we'll move forward with that.
>> I would suggest tableabling it to the to
the second meeting of September. Um
>> that's correct.
>> Okay. Is that
>> that's what I was saying.
>> Or the next committee meeting. Um
>> I was going to say it doesn't need to go
through.
>> Yeah. Just this would be the first time
that this is introduced. Uh, so
councelor Diaz, would you like to um I
mean this is a bill that you're bringing
up through your committee. So you can
either speak to the bill and address
your committee members or you can table
it to the next committee meeting in
November
>> to the second meeting.
>> Correct.
>> I'm sorry, excuse me. October.
>> Would you like to make a motion
councelor Diaz to move
>> motion's on the table
>> to then which meeting?
>> I'm moving it to the second
basically the meeting. the end of
September.
>> Um, and Mr. Harris, correct me if I'm
wrong, but I believe this has to go
through committee. So, the first meeting
in November would be the or the
committee meeting in November is when
>> committee of se well, is it September?
>> Excuse me. October. I'm skipping a month
here.
>> All right. Well,
that would be the first committee
meeting then in October. And hopefully
I'll get a response.
Thank you.
That motion's on there.
I'm sorry. So, it's uh motion is to move
it to the October committee meeting.
>> Committee meeting.
>> Okay.
>> Anybody wants
>> I would second the motion to table this
until the October meeting of the public
safety committee.
>> All in favor?
>> I.
>> And that's all that public safety has at
this.
>> Thank you, Council Diaz. We will now
move to the committee of the whole. Uh
we have three items on the agenda for
this evening. Uh first is council
resolution number 56 2025 which is
recognizing welcoming week. All
counselors received this resolution and
it's celebrating welcoming week from
September 12th to September 21st and
honoring our neighbors from all around
the world who have come to Lancaster and
made this their home. Uh it also
celebrates Lancaster as a certified
welcoming city by welcoming America.
>> Motion to approve. I have a motion.
Have a motion in a second. All those in
favor?
>> I I
>> kind of skipped comment, but
I I will open it up if council uh would
like to have any questions or comments
on the resolution
or from the public.
Move on to council resolution number 57
recognizing Hispanic Heritage Month.
This resolution is honoring Hispanic
Heritage Month from September 15th to
October 15th. Uh I also note that there
is a Hispanic Heritage Month celebration
on October 4th in Ule Plaza and Bins
Park. So if you like to salsa dance, I'm
sure there's going to be some of that
happening in the park. Uh Hispanic
Heritage Month celebration, excuse me.
Uh the city of Lancaster is also
accepting nominations for the Hispanic
Community Achievement Award. Um, and
those applications for nominations are
um, being accepted until September 19th.
So, if you know someone um, in the
community who has had uh, an impact in
the Hispanic community here in
Lancaster, I highly encourage you to
nominate them. Um, with that, uh, any
questions or comments from council,
from the public?
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Um, I think this is a good
resolution, but I do have a request of
council for the future. Um,
I didn't realize until, I'd say, a month
ago that there was an executive order
that determined English is the national
language of the United States. Uh, I've
long enjoyed the fact that that wasn't
the case. I think that Langster needs to
consider making Spanish an official
second language to the city. I think
there's enough contributions by the
Hispanic community and Spanish speakers
that it validates it. I mean, even the
agendas at these meetings are now
bilingual, which is a great thing. I
think Langston City should formalize
Spanish as an official second language
in the government. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Dastro.
Any additional public comment?
>> Mr. Vice President, where might people
go to nominate their fellow community
members?
>> Oh, that's a good question. Uh I am not
sure. Um Mayor Sarra by chance do you
know the link on this? It is on the city
of Lancaster website. Uh city of
lancasterpa.gov.
>> It ishispanic-heritage-mark.
Thank you councelor.
>> Thank you.
>> Awesome. With that, I will hear a motion
to move resolution number 57 to the next
uh full council meeting on September
9th.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> Uh we have a motion and a second. All
those in favor?
>> I
>> I. Third item on the agenda is council
resolution number 58 supporting
legislation for community solar
facilities. And I believe that was
brought forward by councelor Hirs.
>> Uh thank you, Vice President Royo. Um,
this resolution I'm uh bringing forward
to you all. Um, I I sent you so all some
information um yesterday about uh what
this legislation is in Harrisburg. I
have a little blurb. Um, but I wanted to
give a shout out to Elizabeth Hoffman um
who's a resident who encouraged uh me to
bring this forward um endorsing some
really good legislation that uh has
passed the Pennsylvania House um and is
currently sitting in committee in the
Pennsylvania State Senate. Um, so what I
wrote about it is as follows. Um,
community solar enabling legislation
being considered in Harrisburg makes it
possible for all Pennsylvania residents
to source their electricity from solar.
Um, many people that would like to
install solar panels maybe don't have
the space or the proper roof to install
them. Um, I imagine this is a lot of
folks living in Lancaster City uh who
may not have a lot of roof space or the
proper roof um could then source uh
their electricity from solar with uh the
creation of community energy programs
and specifically community solar
programs. Uh with community uh solar,
you can purchase or lease a share of uh
in a community solar project or start a
project with your neighbors um if you're
able to do so. Every month you receive a
credit on your electricity bill for the
energy uh produced by your share. Senate
Bill 504 is the legislation we would
endorse uh with the passage of this
resolution. Uh this is the enabling
legislation that will provide and create
a framework for the creation of
community energy facilities in
Pennsylvania. Um there are currently I
think 24 states that have this
legislation in place. Um it passed on a
bipartisan vote in the Pennsylvania
state house by a vote of 114 nays to 89
nays and was referred to the consumer
protection and professional lensure
committee in the Pennsylvania state
senate. Um increasing community solar
facilities will increase green energy
production in Pennsylvania. There are
235 proposed uh community solar
facilities that a Penn State uh study
would suggest would add 520 permanent
jobs across the Commonwealth and create
800 or sorry$83.3 million of economic
activity. In particular, uh I personally
think about the fact that just a couple
miles outside the city, we have, you
know, farms and other large land owners
that could really benefit from something
like this, uh from constructing small
sale smallcale solar, which I'll add. Um
is not subject to as much regulatory
scrutiny as like large scale solar
farms. Um so there's less, you know,
kind of hoops that have to be jumped
through to make these happen. Um and
I'll add but would you know these would
add to the community energy supply
increase grid resilience by
decentralizing um creating decentralized
sources of energy. Uh the last note I'll
add is that this uh Senate Bill 504 is
part of a series of legislation uh
supported by uh Pennsylvania Governor
Shapiro as part of his lightning plan um
to increase energy production and in
particular renewable energy production
in Pennsylvania. Um, I'll stop there,
but I will take any comments from
council.
Thank you, councils.
And if there are none, I will open up to
comments from the public.
I'm Elizabeth Hoffman, uh, 200 block of
East Ross, and thank you very much,
councelor Hirs, for taking this on. I'm
with a group called Third Act
Pennsylvania. Um, it's people in their
third act of life. We're working on
climate change and um, democracy. And,
um,
this is a big focus of our work. We're
working with a lot of other
organizations
in like a a group called our solar PA
and uh Pennsylvania has been trying to
pass this for 10 years now. This is like
the 11th year. It's a great way for
people who can't afford to put solar on
their roof or if their house is too
shady or they're renters, whatever, they
subscribe to a solar project. So,
they're not actually owning it, leasing
it or anything. and they're just
subscribing it. And I did have this in
Maryland and it's, you know, you don't
notice it on your bill. There's
consolidated billing. So, you just
select that you want to subscribe to a
project and uh you get a credit and
you're putting solar electrons on the
grid.
So, um, Pennsylvania is 49th. It ranks
49th in, uh, the growth of renewable
energy. So, we're really falling behind.
We only, we get less than 1% of our
energy from solar. So, we think this is
a an easy way to add solar to the grid.
And thank you again for considering it.
>> Are there any other comments from the
public?
I'm here to support Mrs. Hoff, Miss
Hoffman. And uh I just wanted to say I
just think this is a great idea, but I'm
kind of wondering
why uh people can't do this already. I
mean, like what about this bill makes
this it people able to do it? Does any
do you know like why why do we need this
bill so that people can do this?
Is it federal federally not allowed?
State not allowed. Yeah, I think we
should do this.
And I'll just I was just going to
quickly add just from the research that
I had been doing um a lot of it is just
about setting up a
like a I mean I hate to use the word
framework because that sounds very I
don't know I don't know what the other
word would be but just kind of
like like creating a system to expedite
the process of creating community solar.
Yeah.
It's
correct. Yes.
Are there any other comments from the
public?
Uh I'll just echo
um uh what Miss Huffman just said is uh
we're uh their organization is trying to
get as many municipalities to support
this as possible to you know kind of
create uh positive momentum to get the
Senate to pass this.
Thank you, councelor Hirs, for bringing
this forward. Um, do I hear a motion to
move resolution number 58 to full
counsel?
>> I'll make a mot
so moved.
>> I'll second.
>> We have a motion and second. All those
in favor?
>> I I
>> I.
>> That concludes our agenda for this
evening. Um, final item for tonight is
the clerk's report and I believe Mr.
Harris submitted that in writing. Are
you okay if we uh skip the verbal
report?
>> Yes, I am. Thank you, Mr. Harris. Uh,
with that, I'll uh hear a motion to
adjourn the committee meeting.
>> Motion to adjurnn.
>> Second.
>> All those in favor? All right. Hi